Guide to the Ralph Leslie Rusk Papers, 1782-1981
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Ralph Leslie Rusk papers 1782-1981
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Rusk, Ralph Leslie.
30 Linear Feet 25,276 Items
Professor of American Literature at Columbia University, 1925-1953. One of the founders of the journal American Literature. Married Clara Gibbs in 1915.
The Ralph Leslie Rusk Papers span the years 1782-1981, and chiefly concern Rusk's teaching and research in American Literature, notably the life and letters of Ralph Waldo Emerson. The collection contains research papers and notebooks, and travel diaries related to Rusk's research and teaching; a large series of correspondence covering the years 1912-1963; teaching materials such as lecture notes; clippings files and articles related to Rusk's publications and related activities; many photographs; Rusk, Gibbs, and Emerson family papers; and papers relating to his wife, Clara Gibbs, including a scrapbook and wedding mementoes. Some of the papers and photographs refer to a period of time spent teaching in the Philippines, around 1912-1914. Collection is minimally processed and described. Acquired as part of the Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Ralph Leslie Rusk Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1978, and 1985-1987.
Collection Overview
The Ralph Leslie Rusk Papers span the years 1782-1981, and chiefly concern Rusk's teaching and research in American Literature, notably the life and letters of Ralph Waldo Emerson. The collection contains research papers and notebooks, and travel diaries related to Rusk's research and teaching; a large series of correspondence covering the years 1912-1963; teaching materials such as lecture notes; clippings files and articles related to Rusk's publications and related activities; many photographs; Rusk, Gibbs, and Emerson family papers; and papers relating to his wife, Clara Gibbs, including a scrapbook and wedding mementoes. Some of the papers and photographs refer to a period of time spent teaching in the Philippines, around 1912-1914. The collection is minimally processed and was originally arranged by additions, described below in more detail. Some boxes have been reordered to reflect a chronological or topical sequence, thus, some box numbers appear out of order.
The original collection (6-19-78) (32 items; dated 1939-1956) contains an essay on William Peterfield Trent, and 31 letters regarding Rusk’s academic activities. There are letters from Bliss Perry, Stanley T. Williams, Henry A. Pochmann, George C. D. Odell, Newton Arvin, John Erskine, Randall Stewart, Harry H. Clark, and Ernest E. Leisy.
The addition (9-25-85) (5982 items; dated 1880-1979) relates primarily to Rusk’s research for editing The Letters of Ralph Waldo Emerson, and his teaching. Rusk maintained journals and ledgers during research trips in Europe, where he retraced the travels of Ralph Waldo Emerson. There are photostatic copies of Emerson family letters, articles about Emerson and related topics, and a clippings file featuring reviews of Rusk’s book. In addition, Rusk’s lecture notes are held in three volumes, notebooks, and notecard files. There are also photographs, photograph albums, and letters (1912-1914) from the period Rusk spent as a professor at the University of the Philippines. These items including descriptions of the islands and culture. There are also miscellaneous items and scrapbooks.
The addition (12-18-85) (100 items; dated 1883-1980) contains an inventory and appraisal of Rusk’s private library now housed at Columbia University; as well as Clara Gibbs’ scrapbooks, correspondence, and various commencement invitations. There are also items related to their marriage, including her bride’s book, a wedding announcement, and their marriage certificate.
The addition (6-25-86) (16,920 items; dated 1782-1963) contains correspondence, clippings, travel diaries, and pictures for the Rusk and Gibbs families. The clippings refer to Rusk’s books THE LIFE OF RALPH WALDO EMERSON, LETTERS OF RALPH WALDO EMERSON, and THE LITERATURE OF THE MIDDLE WESTERN FRONTIER. The correspondence pertains to Rusk’s research and teaching.
The addition (87-116) (12 items; dated 1941-1981) comprises official documents concerning the deaths of Rusk family members. Acquired as part of the Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
American literature -- History and criticism
American literature -- Study and teaching
Columbia University -- Faculty
Diaries
Emerson family
Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803-1882
Gibbs, Clara
Gibbs family
Philippines -- Description and travel
Philippines -- Pictorial works
Photographs
Rusk family
Rusk, Ralph L. (Ralph Leslie), b. 1888
Scrapbooks
University of the Philippines -- Faculty
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1912-1963, (32 boxes)
  Boxes of minimally processed materials have been reorganized into chronological sequence; box numbers therefore appear out of order.
  - Correspondence ca. 1912-1950s (Box 13)
  - Letters, 1913-1923 (Box 29)
  - Letters, 1923-1925 (Box 30)
  - Letters, 1925-1927 (Box 31)
  - Letters, 1926-1927 (Box 32)
  - Letters, 1928 (Box 33)
  - Letters, 1929 (Box 34)
  - Letters, 1931 (Box 35)
  - Letters, 1932 (Box 36)
  - Letters, 1933-1934 (Box 37)
  - Letters, 1939 (Box 38)
  - Letters, 1940-1949 (Box 39)
  - Letters, 1943-1944 (Box 40)
  - Letters, 1949 (Box 41)
  - Letters, 1949-1951 (Box 42)
  - Letters, 1952 (Box 43)
  - Letters, 1953-1954 (Box 44)
  - Letters, 1955-1956 (Box 45)
  - Letters, 1957 (Box 46)
  - Letters, 1958 (Box 6)
  - Letters, 1959 (Box 7)
  - Letters, 1960 (Box 8)
  - Letters, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - Letters - Travel (Box 12)
  - Photocopies of Emerson letters (Box 9)
  - Emerson research: photocopies of Emerson letters (Box 10)
  - Transcriptions of Emerson letters (Box 11)
  - Photocopies of Emerson letters, articles (Box 24)
  - Photocopies of Emerson letters (Box 25)
  - Photocopies of Emerson letters (Box 48)
  - Clara Gibbs Rusk letters (Box 49)
- Writings, (7 boxes)
  - Reviews of Writings (Box 5)
  - Writings by Rusk: Novel (Box 14)
  - Writings by Rusk (Box 16)
  - Writings by Rusk (Box 17)
  - Writings - Miscellaneous Authors (Box 28)
  - Writings: Novel (Box 56)
  - Writings: Novel (Box 57)
- Photographs, 1880-1981, (3 boxes)
  - Family Pictures,1880-1981, bulk 1880-1930 (Box 3)
  - Pictures (Box 23)
    - Tenure as professor at the University of the Philippines, 1912-1914
    - Family Pictures
  - Family Pictures (Box 50)
- Miscellaneous Material, (16 boxes)
  - Clippings (Box 4)
  - Lecture Notes (Box 15)
  - Notebooks and Journals (Box 18)
  - Notebooks of Lecture Notes (Box 19)
  - Lecture Notes (Box 20)
  - Miscellany (Box 21)
  - Clippings (Box 22)
  - Miscellany (Box 26)
  - Clara Gibbs Rusk Papers (Box 27)
  - Gilbert Imlay Research (Box 47)
  - Personal Papers, Diaries (Box 51)
  - Student Enrollment Books [closed to access] (Box 52)
  - Recordings (Box 53)
  - Scrapbook (Box 54)
  - Card Files, Playbills (Box 55)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 58)
- 1987 Accession, (1 folder)
  Comprises official documents concerning the deaths of Rusk family members. Located in Box 58.
- Oversize Material, (2 folders)
  - Three diplomas (Box Sec. A OV8)
  - Emerson genealogy